Alright, so what is the draw of using Python? How is it different from other languages?
What advantages does it offer? Python is the dynamic programming language and this really caught me
by surprise at first. It was created by Guido Van Rossam in the late 1980s. That means that Python
is 30 years old. That means that it's older than some of you. It is old enough to vote.
So a lot of folks think that Python is a new language or that it's new on the scene. That
is not true. It's just been gaining a lot of popularity and probably the past 10 years or so.
There's also this common misconception that Python is only a scripting language. It's really
simple and that is not true at all. Django, a web framework that's built in Python, is used to
run Instagram, which is one of the largest websites in the world with the most users. It powers
parts of Reddit. It's used at Netflix and early versions of Dropbox were built almost entirely in Python.
Dropbox credits a lot of it's success to Python because Python is easy to read and easy to
write and it's easy for teams to collaborate in Python. They have this idea and they were able to get
a product out the door as quickly as possible and then when they had to scale that was something
that they started dealing with by replacing parts of their application with go or other more
performant languages but they didn't optimize when they didn't need to and that let them have this
very, very successful company. It's also becoming an increasingly popular language for education
of all ages. There is our Python books for kids. Python is taught in universities and
I found this great quote that in 2014 Python was the most popular teaching language at top
US universities and if you know Python you might not have a hard time finding a job because it's one
of the fastest growing programming languages. Gido said that Python is now also the language of
amateurs and I mean that in the best way possible. That means that the language is accessible to a lot of
people. One of the great things of Python is that it's open source. It's an active development.
There's a committed team of core contributors and there are also a lot of issues that are tagged
welcoming for beginners. So as you advance in your Python journey if you decide that you want to
contribute back to the language that is something that you can easily do. We chatted a little bit
about versions in Python. You might hear something about Python 2 versus Python 3. What's that all about?
It will say that this is maybe a little bit of a stain on Python history. Python 3 was actually
released in 2008 and its adoption was very slow. There were a lot of really popular frameworks that
didn't want to migrate because it would have been a lot of work and because of that a lot of folks
stuck to Python 2 instead of Python 3 there were some breaking changes that were introduced.
At this point that chapter is now fully closed. Python 2 7 which was the last version of Python 2
is deprecated. It has reached its end of life. It's not getting critical security updates. It's not
getting critical new features that you might want to use. So it's time to use Python 3 and move on
from Python 2. All of those popular libraries and frameworks have now migrated as well and are
likely not supporting their Python 2 features because that's double the work. So this course is going
to focus on Python 3 only and I would encourage you all to use Python 3 for your personal projects
and projects at work. Python has an incredibly rich, fully featured standard library.
There's a saying that Python is batteries included. So anything that you might want to do like
working with. Jason, all of those are included in the standard library. You don't need to install
any additional packages and there's a link here into the standard library and you kind of go
through here and see what is available. There's a lot of stuff. There's also the Python package
index for third party packages. As of today there are almost 300,000 projects and almost half a
million users. So this is where you go where you want to find something that's maybe more modern
or more niche and there are lots of third party packages available for many different uses.
There's tons of stuff for AI and ML, sci-fi, numpy pandas, pi torch. There are great options
for hardware and microcontrollers. There are two very popular web development frameworks that
are Django and Flask, lots of tooling for DevOps and the absolute best part of Python is actually
the incredible community. So after this course I encourage you all to continue in that community,
Python US is the biggest yearly conference with approximately 4,000 attendees. There are lots of local
user groups. A lot of them are listed in a wiki that is linked. A lot of these groups are now
having online and remote events that you can participate in. And there are also many great and
supportive groups for women and non-binary developers such as Pilates and Django girls. And these
organizations tend to have chapters in most major cities and they do a lot of really, really great work.
So a little bit about the philosophy of Python. A lot of ideas in Python were formed by something
called the Zen of Python. It's a collection of 19 software principles that was sent to the Python
mailing list in 1999. And you can actually find the Zen of Python included in the Python distribution
as an Easter egg. So let's go to our repel wherever you have that open and type import this.
And we're not going to read this whole thing but the the top few tenants
beautiful is better than ugly, explicit is better than implicit, simple is better than complex,
complex is better than complicated. Flat is better than nested, sparse is better than dense,
and most importantly readability counts. So as you advance through your Python career, you'll see
more and more of this in practice. Python code should be simple. You shouldn't try to make
the most the the smallest one liner that nobody else can understand. Python can give you those tools.
You can do it but you shouldn't. You should focus on making your code very clear, very simple,
very readable. Flat is better than nested means don't have a arrow-shaped code. So no,
if statement, if statement, if statement, if statement, not a ton of nested loops. Try to keep
everything as close to the left margin as possible. And really focus on this. This is what makes
Python different from a lot of other programming languages. Now, a way that Python encourages you
to write simple readable code is with a style guideline that's included in the
languages list of official proposals. It's called Pep 8. And if we take a look at this,
Pep 8 gives coding conventions for Python. Everything from indentation to maximum line length
to where blank lines should be to where how the spacing around equal sign works. You don't have
to remember all of these rules because tools called linters, you should have installed a
inter-invious code. We'll show you warnings when your code doesn't meet Pep 8 standards.
Know that the warnings that linters give, they're not syntax errors. Your code will still run,
but it won't be accepted Python code style standards. Not very important when you're working on
your own, but much more important when you're working on a team and collaborating with others.
There are a few other Easter eggs that I'm going to show you. Actually, I don't know if this
one works in Python 3. This was a Python 2 Easter egg. There we go. So, if you type from underscore
underscore future import braces, like we'll Python the programming language ever get braces.
You'll see a syntax error and the message is not a chance.
So, Python won't be looking like JavaScript anytime in the near future. And then,
one of my favorite Easter eggs is if you import anti-gravity.
This will take you to an XKCD comic about Python that says you're flying how
with Python. I learned it last night. Everything is so simple. Hello world is just print
hello world. This is Python 2 and Python 3 you need those parentheses. So, yeah, Python's a pretty
fun language, but it's also very, very powerful. We're going to take a short break before we talk
about the anatomy of a Python program and jump into data types.